So what is the point of celibacy
in terms of practice? What is what is
the point of it? Cuz many people are
celibate when they're not having sexual
when they're not having sexual
relations.
Uhhuh. So what why is complete celibacy
So what why is complete celibacy
important for practice? Right.
Well, you can you can say
you can say that even out of the the
practice of a Buddhist monk or or just
in general uh celibacy would be
beneficial even for for a non Buddhist
even for a non Buddhist person. Um, and
the most obvious reason why that would
be is because uh uh you're not
controlled. You're not giving in to a
very um very a very powerful desire that
otherwise controls and shapes up your
whole life.
Cuz again, regardless whether people
practicing dumb or not, uh sensuality
and uh sexuality,
it defines quite a lot of people's
lives. Certainly has probably the
strongest influence
Um so if you were to um
adopt celibacy as a practice means you
will be going against that against that
uh that desire that pull which means you
will be developing your mind in regard
to that
cuz cuz as you said yeah sometimes
people are celibate when when they're
not having sexual intercourse but that's
not celibacy because when the
opportunity comes they're going to have
sexual intercourse But the point is to
to take it on as a as a determination,
as a practice.
Um, and then uh then obviously it's much
harder in the same sense if somebody's
trying to give up smoking. It's much
harder to give up smoking if you if you
decide to never smoke again as opposed
to if you think okay I won't smoke for a
month then even the heaviest of the
smokers can make it can last for a month
but not if you decided it for the rest
of your life. So you can imagine how
much more that is with celibacy. But
that's that's what I mean like if
somebody does have the strength of the
mind to come to the point of determining
an act of celibacy means then the mind
can start to develop on that level in
that regard.
And uh yeah if a person is celibate they
they will eventually it takes time to
kind of dry the mind out from the sort
of wetness of desires. Uh but once the
mind is dried out then uh literally
everything else in the life in the world
that was depending upon non celebrity
the celibacy they're free of
okay so like beauty making yourself
beautiful well everything your identity basically
well everything your identity basically
your identity would fail if a if a if a
if a person who doesn't practice dharma
say go beyond sensuality sexuality
through practice of celibacy and they
free themselves from sensual cravings
They would to greater degree be freer of
their own ego as well and the conceit
and all the suffering that comes with
it. all the warrior all the anxieties,
let alone if they were to to to sort of
uproot that as well with the right of
view and practice of the dharma
cuz the whole life person's life an
average person life revolves around
following desires and and getting what
you want which usually revolves around
sexuality around you know finding a mate
a family the whole thing revolves around
the the very basic desires that are
deeply rooted obviously. So if if one is
able to go against it in a sense of not
just pure denial but in a sense of
actually develop wisdom on account of it
like seeing the nature of desire by not
giving into that desire you can
eventually overcome that desire and then
you can imagine the freedom of that
mind. Well the Buddha compared it to
being free like being in prison then
being let out of the prison crossing the
desert not knowing if you're going to
make it to the other end and then you
make it to the other end. It's like a
huge relief, huge burden. And again, I'm
talking even for somebody who is not
practicing the dharma, just sort of
doesn't want to give into their desires
anymore and then overcomes that, they
they would have quite a lot of uh
release and relief.
[Music]
But most people won't do that.
No, no, of course. Cuz it's way too
hard. Yeah, it's way too hard for most
people. Um that's why it's it's highly
unlikely that anybody will do it today
outside of some sort of
philosophy or religious practice. Um
because it's just there wouldn't be
enough motivation because it's too high.
Back in the day there were back in the
Buddhist time there were people who were
just practicing for the sake of freedom
and desire. They were not necessarily
followers of the dharma or anything
else. And that's why did say people
outside of this disposition can free
themselves from these various forms of
um uh
holding and um attachments and
assumptions and uh sensual desire was one of them.
But it's it's not just about
giving up celibacy in Buddhist teaching.
It's not just about giving up sex. It's
not just about giving up masturbation or
not seeing women or not seeing men.
Yeah. What I read it's more about
What I read it's more about
delighting your own sexuality. That is
the true set of not the lighting in your
own sexual
Well, it has to Okay, I see what you
mean. Yeah. It it has to start simply by
giving up simply by saying no. But yeah,
that is just the that is just the first
step that you have to then go beyond if
you really want to be free. Otherwise,
you have to spend your whole life just
saying no. But that's not freedom.
That's just resisting it. But yeah,
there wouldn't be no freedom if you
haven't resisted it first. So by
resisting it first, by saying no to
these types of actions in order to
overcome it, then yes, you have to
overcome that sensuality in regard to
yourself. You have to overcome the attitude in
You have to overcome the attitude in
regard to your own body. The attitude
that it's basically um uh regarding the
body as a basis for pleasure
and then you you you see a direct kind
of relationship with the with the
pleasure of your senses. And this
pertains to any type of pleasure, not
necessarily only sexual or something
like that. Any type of pleasure you
gaining through the senses you can
overcome by overcoming basically the
attitude of regarding your body as a
basis for that pleasure. By
appropriating the body, you appropriate
that which body is attracted to. By by
not appropriating the body anymore, you
free yourself from uh from the
counterparts of your sense graces.
So then you're not just resisting
anymore. Then you go beyond. Exactly. Then there
Then you go beyond. Exactly. Then there
is no need for resistance cuz there is
no more pull.
But for as long as you're appropriating
the your senses, your body, uh you will
be pulled. Which means you might spend
the whole life living a celibate life
which is good. It's still better but
it's not it's not leading to wisdom and
it's not leading to freedom from it from
sensuality. Yes.